Guide to the Pam Butler Good Girl Archive ca. 1992-2011 MSS 322
© 2012 Fales Library and Special Collections
Pam Butler Good Girl Archive
ca. 1992-2011
MSS 322
© 2012 Fales Library and Special Collections
5.0 linear feet (4 boxes; 6 photo binders)
This collection contains the original artwork, photocopies, and audio and video recordings produced by the Good Girl and Win street art projects as conceived and executed by artist Pam Butler in Buffalo and New York during the 1990s.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers. Appointments are necessary for the use of manuscript and archival collections. Collection use is subject to all copyright laws. Permission to publish materials must be obtained in writing from the Director of Fales Library and Special Collections. Please contact fales.library@nyu.edu or call 212 998 2596.
Provenance
The contents of the Pam Butler/Good Girl Archive were donated by Pam Butler to the Fales Downtown Collection in 2011.
Scope and Content
The Pam Butler Good Girl Archive is comprised of original artwork, photographs, audio and video recordings, exhibition proposals, and ephemera primarily related to the "Good Girl" and "Win" street art projects produced by Butler in the 1990s. Elements include poster mock-ups and reproductions, project proposals, flyers, posters and postcards. This body of components also includes interviews conducted with Butler, press coverage, and contextual information related to the New York street art milieu of the 1980s and 1990s. There is also professional and personal correspondence, production and personal photography, digital anthologies, and two self-published collections of work.
Biographical
Pam Butler is an American fine artist whose work generally explores ideas of social construction and female identity.
Born in 1956, Butler grew up in the suburbs of Buffalo, New York, and moved to New York City in 1978. In 1992, while working as a bookkeeper, she began pasting homemade posters onto buildings, lamposts, and other city fixtures. The black and white images, done in marker, depicted a stylized woman accompanied by a perjorative ("Good Girl," "Whore," "Angel" etc.). By the end of the year the work had become a familiar presence in lower Manhattan; 10,000 posters, consisting of over 230 drawings, were eventually put up over a two-year period ending in 1994.
Butler's next project, titled "Win," incorporated the cumulative and serendipitous qualities of her earlier street art into an interactive public work. Viewers were invited by Butler's posters and flyers to call and write in to an entity called the Win Line, and share their reactions to various questions related to success ("Have you ever won the lottery?", "Suppose your life ws all over and you hadn't gotten the grand prize yet?"). Responses were recorded on an answering machine, and in public using video.
These projects could be considered in the tradition of other New York street and public artists like Keith Haring, AVANT, and Jenny Holzer. Since the 1990s she has continued to make and exhibit her art. Butler received a MFA from the School of Visual Arts in 1990, and has exhibited at P.S. 122, White Columns, Artists Space, FDR Gallery, and Visual Arts Gallery.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into six series.
Posters
Photographs and Supplemental Material
Video
Audio
Data Storage
Objects
Artists |z New York (State) |z New York.; Audiotapes.; CD-Rs.; Color photographs.; Correspondence.; Feminism and art.; Fliers (printed matter); Graffiti.; Notebooks.; Posters.; street art; Videotapes.
- OVERSIZE Series I: Posters, 2.0 boxes
  - Cover Girl Poster, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Full Set of Good Girl Drawings 1 of 9, 2011 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Full Set of Good Girl Drawings 2 of 9, 2011 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Full Set of Good Girl Drawings 3 of 9, 2011 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Full Set of Good Girl Drawings 4 of 9, 2011 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Full Set of Good Girl Drawings 5 of 9, 2011 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Full Set of Good Girl Drawings 6 of 9, 2011 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Full Set of Good Girl Drawings 7 of 9, 2011 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Full Set of Good Girl Drawings 8 of 9, 2011 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Full Set of Good Girl Drawings 9 of 9, 2011 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Full Set of Win Project Posters, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Good Girl and Win Promotional Posters, 1995, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Good Girl "Jorgonsen" Posters 1 of 3, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Good Girl "Jorgonsen" Posters 2 of 3, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Good Girl "Jorgonsen" Posters 3 of 3, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Misc. [Win Responses, Hag Polaroid], undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Win Poster Mock-Ups, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Win and Good Girl Indelible Posters 1 of 9, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Win and Good Girl Indelible Posters 2 of 9, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Win and Good Girl Indelible Posters 3 of 9, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Win and Good Girl Indelible Posters 4 of 9, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Win and Good GIrl Indelible Posters 5 of 9, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Win and Good Girl Indelible Posters 6 of 9, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Win and Good Girl Indelible Posters 7 of 9, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Win and Good Girl Indelible Posters 8 of 9, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Win and Good Girl Indelible Posters 9 of 9, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Win and Good Girl Poster Copies 1 of 3, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Win and Good Girl Poster Copies 2 of 3, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Win and Good Girl Poster Copies 3 of 3, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Series II: Correspondence and Manuscripts
  - Daily News, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - The Good Girl Book 1 of 2, Undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - The Good Girl Book 2 of 2, Undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - The Good Girl Book (A Book by Pam Butler), Undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Good Girl Book "Working Draft #4", Undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Good Girl Correspondence 1 of 4, 1992, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Good Girl Correspondence 2 of 4, 1993, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Good Girl Correspondence 3 of 4, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Good Girl Correspondence 4 of 4, 1995, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Good Girl Flyers (Small) 1 of 2, Undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Good Girl Flyers (Small) 2 of 2, Undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Good Girl Manuscript & Notes (1st Draft) 1 of 3, Undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Good Girl Manuscript & Notes (1st Draft) 2 of 3, Undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Good Girl Manuscript & Notes (1st Draft) 3 of 3, Undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Good Girl Manuscript (Untitled Draft), Undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Good Girl Press & Proposals 1 of 2, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Good Girl Press & Proposals 2 of 2, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Good Girls Fall In Love Book, undated (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Good Girls Minds Their P's and Q's Book, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Steno Notebook 1 of 2, undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Steno Notebook 2 of 2, undated (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Win Distribution Notes & Pictures, Undated (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - "Win" Flyers (Green) 1 of 2, undated (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - "Win" Miscellany, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Win Project Distribution Documents, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Win Project Questionnaire, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - "Win" Working Flyer, Undated (Box 3, Folder 26)
- Series III: Photographs
  - Photographs, slides and negatives, undated (Binder A)
  - Photographs, slides and negatives, undated (Binder B)
  - Photographs, slides and negatives, undated (Binder C)
  - Photographs, slides and negatives, undated; Photos contained in 8 x 8 box are unsorted and need to be rehoused in archival sleeves in a photo album. (Binder D)
  - Photographs, slides and negatives, undated (Binder E)
  - Photographs, slides and negatives, undated (Binder F)
- Series IV: Video
  Conditions Governing Access
  Access copies do not currently exist for video. Please consult a Fales archivist.
  - Win [Master], undated (Box 4, Media ID: 322.0001)
    Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note
    Format: Ampex UMATIC 187
  - Dub, undated (Box 4, Media ID: 322.0002)
  - Win Video, 1995 (Box 4, Media ID: 322.0003)
    Format: Maxell VHS
  - Untitled I, undated (Box 4, Media ID: 322.0004)
    Format: TDK VHS HD-X
  - 2nd and 3rd Times Out, 1994 (Box 4, Media ID: 322.0005)
    Format: Sony Hi-8
  - 4th Time Out; w/Emily 3/23/95, 1995 (Box 4, Media ID: 322.0006)
  - Event "E" 3/31, undated (Box 4, Media ID: 322.0007)
  - Event "F" 4/7, undated (Box 4, Media ID: 322.0008)
  - Event "G" 4/18, undated (Box 4, Media ID: 322.0009)
  - Mark Event "H" 4/19, undated (Box 4, Media ID: 322.0010)
  - Emily Event "I" 4/28, undated (Box 4, Media ID: 322.0011)
  - Event "I" 5/5, undated (Box 4, Media ID: 322.0012)
  - Event "K", undated (Box 4, Media ID: 322.0013)
  - 1/2 of "Stuff", undated (Box 4, Media ID: 322.0014)
  - Sound Tape 1, undated (Box 4, Media ID: 322.0015)
    Format: TDK 8mm HS
  - Sound Tape 2, undated (Box 4, Media ID: 322.0016)
- Series V: Audio
  Access copies do not currently exist for this audio. Please consult a Fales archivist.
  - Win Line Messages, 1994, 1995 (Box 4, Media ID: 322.0017)
    Format: Maxell XLII Audio Cassette
  - Win Line 4/6 thru 4/21, 1994, 1995 (Box 4, Media ID: 322.0018)
    Format: TDK SA90 Audio Cassette
  - Win Line Messages Tape B 4/20/95, 1995 (Box 4, Media ID: 322.0019)
  - Copy of Message Tape B 4/20 - 9/20, undated (Box 4, Media ID: 322.0020)
  - Karen Events "E" and "F", undated (Box 4, Media ID: 322.0021)
    Format: TDK SD60 Audio Cassette
  - Event "E," "F," and "G", undated (Box 4, Media ID: 322.0022)
  - Stacy Event "G"; Mark Event "H", undated (Box 4, Media ID: 322.0023)
  - Emily Event G and I, undated (Box 4, Media ID: 322.0024)
    Format: TDK SD90 Audio Cassette
  - Rachel w/Salvation Army, undated (Box 4, Media ID: 322.0025)
  - Disc. after w/Actors 12/13, undated (Box 4, Media ID: 322.0026)
  - Emily Event "I" and "G", undated (Box 4, Media ID: 322.0027)
  - Sampler of Win Project Audio (Box 4, Media ID: 322.0028)
  - Radio Bayonne, undated (Box 4, Media ID: 322.0029)
    Format: TDK SA60 Audio Cassette
  - Untitled I, undated (Box 4, Media ID: 322.0030)
  - Untitled II, undated (Box 4, Media ID: 322.0031)
  - God Is My Co-Pilot, "Puss 02", 1995 (Box 4, Media ID: 322.0032)
    Format: Audio CD
  - Actors, undated (Box 4, Media ID: 322.0033)
    Format: Phone-Mate MC-60 Microcassette
  - Emily 3/31; Event "E", undated (Box 4, Media ID: 322.0034)
    Format: Olympus XB60 Microcassette
  - Untitled III, undated (Box 4, Media ID: 322.0035)
  - Mark On Street 11/25, undated (Box 4, Media ID: 322.0036)
  - Untitled IV, undated (Box 4, Media ID: 322.0037)
    Format: TDK MC-5 Microcassette
  - Untitled V, undated (Box 4, Media ID: 322.0038)
  - Untitled VI, undated (Box 4, Media ID: 322.0039)
    Format: TDK MCL-11 Head Cleaner Microcassette
- Series VI: Data Storage
  Access copies do not currently exist for data storage. Please consult a Fales archivist.
  - Good Girl Project 0 thru 6, undated (Box 5, Media ID: 322.3.0001)
    Format: iomega Zip Disk
  - Good Girl Project 7 thru 13, undated (Box 5, Media ID: 322.3.0002)
    Format: Fujifilm Zip Disk
  - Good Girl Project 14 thru 20, undated (Box 5, Media ID: 322.3.0003)
  - Good Girl Project 21 thru 27, undated (Box 5, Media ID: 322.3.0004)
  - Good Girl Project 28 thru 34, undated (Box 5, Media ID: 322.3.0005)
  - Good Girl Project 35 thru 41, undated (Box 5, Media ID: 322.3.0006)
  - Good Girl Project 42 thru 48, undated (Box 5, Media ID: 322.3.0007)
  - Good Girl Project 49 thru 55, undated (Box 5, Media ID: 322.3.0008)
  - Good Girl Project 56 thru 62, undated (Box 5, Media ID: 322.3.0009)
  - Good Girl Project 63 thru 69, undated (Box 5, Media ID: 322.3.0010)
  - Good Girl Project 70 thru 76, undated (Box 5, Media ID: 322.3.0011)
  - Good Girl Project 77 thru 83, undated (Box 5, Media ID: 322.3.0012)
  - Good Girl Project 84 thru 90, undated (Box 5, Media ID: 322.3.0013)
  - Good Girl Project 91 thru 97, undated (Box 5, Media ID: 322.3.0014)
  - Good Girl Project 98 thru 104, undated (Box 5, Media ID: 322.3.0015)
  - Good Girl Project 105 thru 111, undated (Box 5, Media ID: 322.3.0016)
  - Good Girl Project 112 thru 118, undated (Box 5, Media ID: 322.3.0017)
  - Good Girl Project 119 thru 125, undated (Box 5, Media ID: 322.3.0018)
  - Good Girl Project 126 thru 132, undated (Box 5, Media ID: 322.3.0019)
  - Good Girl Project 133 thru 139, undated (Box 5, Media ID: 322.3.0020)
  - Good Girl Project 140 thru 146, undated (Box 5, Media ID: 322.3.0021)
  - Good Girl Project 147 thru 153, undated (Box 5, Media ID: 322.3.0022)
  - Good Girl Project 154 thru 160, undated (Box 5, Media ID: 322.3.0023)
  - Good Girl Project 161 thru 167, undated (Box 5, Media ID: 322.3.0024)
  - Good Girl Project 168 thru 174, undated (Box 5, Media ID: 322.3.0025)
  - Good Girl Project 175 thru 181, undated (Box 5, Media ID: 322.3.0026)
  - Good Girl Project 182 thru 188, undated (Box 5, Media ID: 322.3.0027)
  - Good Girl Project 196 thru 202, undated (Box 5, Media ID: 322.3.0028)
  - Good Girl Project 189 thru 195, undated (Box 5, Media ID: 322.3.0029)
  - Good Girl Project 203 thru 209, undated (Box 5, Media ID: 322.3.0030)
  - Good Girl Project 210 thru 216, undated (Box 5, Media ID: 322.3.0031)
  - Good Girl Project 217 thru 223, undated (Box 5, Media ID: 322.3.0032)
  - Good Girl Project 224 thru 230, undated (Box 5, Media ID: 322.3.0033)
  - Good Girl Project 331 thru 237, undated (Box 5, Media ID: 322.3.0034)
  - Good Girl Project 238 thru 244, undated (Box 5, Media ID: 322.3.0035)
  - Good Girl Project 245 thru 251, undated (Box 5, Media ID: 322.3.0036)
  - Good Girl Project 252 thru 258, undated (Box 5, Media ID: 322.3.0037)
  - Good Girl Project 259 thru 265, undated (Box 5, Media ID: 322.3.0038)
  - Good Girl Project 266 thru 272, undated (Box 5, Media ID: 322.3.0039)
  - Good Girl Project 273 thru 279, undated (Box 5, Media ID: 322.3.0040)
  - Good Girl Project 280 thru 283, undated (Box 5, Media ID: 322.3.0041)
  - Jorgenson, undated (Box 5, Media ID: 322.3.0042)
  - Good Girl Project / Pam Butler, undated (Box 5, Media ID: 322.3.0043)
  - Good Girl Images, undated (Box 5, Media ID: 322.3.0049)
    Format: Kodak Digital Science Photo CD
  - Good Girl Book 4/2/04, 2004 (Box 5, Media ID: 322.3.0044)
    Format: Office Depot CD-R
  - Good Girl Book 4/28/05, 2005 (Box 5, Media ID: 322.3.0045)
  - Good Girl Book Draft, 2009 (Box 5, Media ID: 322.3.0046)
    Format: Hewlett-Packard CD-R
  - Good Girl Book Working Draft, undated (Box 5, Media ID: 322.3.0047)
    Format: Staples CD-R
  - Good Girl Book Working PDF, undated (Box 5, Media ID: 322.3.0048)
- Series VII: Objects
  - Olympus Pearlcorder S924 Microcassette Recorder, undated (Box 4, Object ID: 322.2.0001)
  - Sony Cassette-Corder, undated (Box 4, Object ID: 322.2.0002)